Call it over the record schedule made in my city council for Tuesday January 16th, 2024, to
Buck and put up scheduled personal experiences. We have none. Three claims last.
For the need to approval of the minutes for October 28 special meeting December 6th special meeting.
Both those in 23 and January 2nd and 24.
You said you said that. No. You're here in 20. Wow. I already stated November 28th,
join 23 special meeting. December 6th, 23 special meeting.
January 2nd, 24, regular meeting.
Hi. Hi. Hi.
By the needy crisis center outside organization update and discussion.
My name is Kelsey Samuels and the Executive Director of the Community Crisis Center.
I'm here because we get a utility waiver from you guys every year.
So I'm just going to give you a little bit of an update of who we are and what we do and answer any questions that you guys have.
So we're a local nonprofit. We serve victims of domestic violence, sexual assault and stalking.
And we are actually regional. We're auto-adelleware and credit counties, but we're headquartered here in Ottawa County.
We have our only shelter for the region and then walk in office.
So our shelter house last year, 219 people.
Just to kind of give you guys a scope that domestic violence shelters in Tulsa, Noctoma City house about 400 people a year.
So here in Miami, we are more than doubled that.
We have one of the most high revolving domestic violence shelters in a rural area in the state.
We also have our office. So last year we had our highest service year to date.
We serve 784 total clients.
We have almost doubled the amount of clients that we've served over the last four years.
So the need for services is great. I'm sure you guys have heard of Oklahoma's currently number one in the nation for rates of domestic violence.
We're also number two in the nation for the rate that women are murdered by an intimate partner.
So it's a huge problem in our state. Our agency provides no cost services to any victim in need.
Our shelter which is where we get the waiver.
77 of our clients were children. So we have a lot of kids that come through. We have a child advocacy program that focuses specifically on their needs.
We do counseling, support groups. We have two embedded legal aid attorneys.
So they can provide pro bono legal assistance, completely no cost to any of our clients in need.
We do safety planning, advocacy, we can help people.
Presumers get them in a housing.
But I always sell people the emergency shelter component, not everybody wants to go there.
Nobody really wakes up and says I want to leave all my stuff and go stay in a shelter.
So people that come to us, they are usually in crisis.
There are need a lot of times law enforcement or bring people to us.
We have an agreement with all of the people.
departments that even if we're full, if they go to a situation and they have a victim and
they're needing to split people up or get someone somewhere we will always take them.
When I came on seven years ago, we had 18 beds, we now have 24 beds, we have three sleeper
sofas, we're always full, there's never a night that we don't have somebody on a couch.
So we provide our critical service to the community and I'd be happy to answer any other
questions you guys have.
I've never been turned down one time, to bring somebody there, to bring somebody there.
And that class you all had last week, I learned that we need more of that.
Yeah, that's we do provide training as well to law enforcement.
So the way where we give you, is that for all of your buildings here now?
No, it's just for our shelter and it is for a portion of our utilities there.
A lot of people assume that agencies like ours are completely granted and we're not, we have
to raise a lot of money locally.
And then as you guys know, cost of everything has gone up significantly, but we get a $10,000 utility
credit every year which is very helpful.
So we're 24, seven, our shelter is always open, our hotlines always open, we run our hotline out
of there.
We had over 1600 crisis calls in chat last year, so those are people calling us at 2am on the weekend,
a lot of people present at shelter not during business hours, so we always have staffing there
and we'll always take clients, it doesn't matter when it happens.
Does anybody know what the total utility bill is for the year?
I know, but they have to do that, they just need to do that.
So from July 1st?
It depends on the year, but we're usually over 20,000 here.
So we're kind of chatting our friends there about the race.
Is that something we can do?
We would have to review the budget, obviously since all of our funds were budgeted, we'd have to go
to identify the projects that are not completed or that could be bumped this fiscal year
and basically doing a mid-ment to the budget.
Do you agree with that, Joe?
Is there an alternate path?
So it's a credit.
Okay.
So we're going to be in the contract.
I mean, Ben and Walzworth, I see what these people do, and they do a phenomenal job.
I mean, we need to try to do whatever we can to help them.
So Jim, I've really just amount to what I've reduced.
revenue. So that would be able to give us you any side. You'd see reduced revenue
as far as the industry. So another question that I'm with the latter. I know
myself and each councilman has a little fund that they can use for community stuff. Would
this be one of those thoughts? Yeah, I mean theoretically because to Jill's point, it's
really just a waiver of the utility bill and it's on two different sides. One general fund.
Once of issue A, but I mean, ultimately we could net it out.
Well, I mean, I just wrote down we need to do more.
That's what I'm interested in, where I come from, I'm not so much interested in
because it's going to be put to good use. So I guess we're looking for you for
a recommendation then on where it comes from, but I guess.
Now we sell back the historical utilization and come up with a recommendation
recommend using some of the councils. Well, I don't want to speak for these guys on that.
Well, I'll just make a recommendation. I don't really care. I mean, you're half over and
way you do yes. We can bring a recommendation for that.
So what do you want for us tonight? We're going to take a look. We're going to try to get you some more.
We appreciate it. We're very grateful for this sport. And the only thing I wanted to add
I forgot earlier is we are currently in process the training we have last week to get certified
to provide services also to human trafficking victims. It's currently only three programs
in the state of Oklahoma that provide that. So we're really excited to be able to
bring that regionally. We've had four survivors of trafficking present to our agency in the last six weeks.
So that's something that will be moving towards a later in 2024, but we're working with the attorney
general's office on that right now.
And it's only going to get worse.
I want to grow houses sometimes like that. It's only getting worse.
And I don't know if you guys have been out to New York City or not, but we're lucky to have her.
She's a rock star in our community. She really is she runs a tight ship out there
and she gives those the victims what they need and I really applaud her for her efforts.
We're lucky to have her a promise. So we're going to table this right.
So we'll table this and we'll somebody we'll get back with you.
Thank you guys so much.
All right.
Thank you.
Six minus senior center outside organization.
That big discussion.
Sagmar Walther.
But I don't see.
Dagmar has requested to change to the February 5th.
Great.
We will table that one.
So appointment.
Bo Reese and Tyler Collin has the 2024 representatives
to the Graham Gateway Board of Directors for a one year turn.
We'll be meeting February 20, 2024.
Motion.
Second.
Open.
Hi.
He's that.
Sorry.
All right.
Eight mayors and automations to point itself to the by the CVB.
Board is expissive.
You want to make a motion too?
I don't think I can do that.
I'll make a motion to approve.
I'll second.
I don't call.
All right.
That's.
Nine.
Award C. 23.
That's.
Six.
Nine.
For my original airport.
New turn.
All construction across the construction.
Not to exceed.
To that two million.
$619.
And the.
The contract.
Continue to upon the submission of.
All required contract document.
Documents and authorize.
The city manager has designated the sign.
Those to proceed.
Two millions.
That's a question.
$619.
I would even want to say anything.
Because I heard from earlier.
So.
Two million.
Six hundred.
And nineteen thousand.
Sorry.
So who had to bid our most.
The bid.
Mine was.
Two million.
Six hundred and ninety thousand.
The other two were two.
Nine and.
And three.
A frequent one.
Our projected.
Budget.
Was said.
For bid estimates.
About 2.1.
Two point one change.
Total.
For.
$137,000.
A bit of.
A budget.
We have.
Going to the.
Contract.
Cross one.
It's in.
We use the value of the.
To.
Pets.
We are.
To use.
To.
And.
to take a chunk of that narrow down, we're going tomorrow, probably cross one, and have a
discussion with that on some value engineering and see where we can trim that down a little bit.
We're doing the best to be brutal, but this is just working and I was a close project that
was presented. We are asking to approve the cross and contract to the city manager of the
person to decide to permit for, permit for, permit for saying that it's for noticing a
certain that the council agrees to.
Do you think we should wait until that we have a meeting with Crosswind to see where you can
trim more priciness or cross-hent?
We have our time on, we'd like to get a kind of approval to take them to the city manager
of the person to do that, and we can get that number instead of having to come back.
Just because our timeline for the better answer was, we're excited.
We got a meeting next week, right?
Yes.
We have a work study.
I'd be interested to see where they can cut more costs at 2.1 budget, and then 2.6 bid.
Could we approve the not to exceed tonight, like 2.2?
Two crosswind?
I mean, two.
Well, I don't think you'd be able to get there.
All right.
I said I'll think you'd be able to buy else this evening.
No.
I was worried.
There are 300,000 cheaper than the next one.
And I said what?
You know, close one.
My thoughts are that if we approve a 2.2 not to exceed, then I think crossing is more likely to
meet us there.
Just my thoughts.
And because it's already approved.
Yeah.
That's that.
Yep.
I think the city is going on for their assistance and probably get it down anyway.
So I'm not comfortable approving it at 2.6.
Right.
That's what I say.
It's at 2.1 something.
So we do a 2.2 not to exceed.
So if they say no on the 2.2, we revend.
We can do it.
We do it.
I think this point starts with the arms off the building.
We're saving parts of the project.
And you did that number.
There were some options there that we did to remove.
There's not a lot left, we pretty extensive meetings with the engineers going through.
We already reduced the overall footprint and officers.
Things like that had to remove some security frames.
All of our officers out of work files, the parking lot.
There was some experience.
That's why we're really wanting to go through this point.
We're going to go to the negotiations with the Crossland.
To see where we can get just because of the last thing we want to do is start cutting even more.
We're getting up with just a 10 bucks.
But I think we can get the other.
Yeah, I think we can get the other.
What do you think in terms of?
I know, my health is where I need to cross the Marrow and honor be.
It's like a lot of them did.
A lot of health be.
So do I have the border and I guess?
What do you want to thought it's on the Snaps or exceed number?
I don't know.
That was our national number.
I think it was too.
Yeah, it was too.
Because it was one from the stake and one from us.
That was our national number.
And we did.
The Council when we came in the other room and in the big presentation.
It was 2.1.
There was 2.1.
We agreed on 2.1.
Whatever was anyone.
And that was just.
Did we know that exact number?
Anybody?
2.1.
Ninety two.
Yes, he knows.
Approximately.
Two.
Seven.
One.
Eight.
Ninety two.
So if we just do it not to exceed 2.2, we're pretty much about it.
I'll just make motion.
We vote not to exceed 2.2.
Second.
It's a thankless job and you know everybody is going to complain when their lights are on or their water is not running and that's how it is
But I just want to make sure we recognize him and
Maybe if I have any more money left over and have a hot dog feed form or something when all the cold weather passes
We'll just have to do something
Maybe we'll need to get together and power money and I want to say thank you to the city for opening up the
Civic Center for shelter and
And for all the people's help this help with that
That's been awesome. I know there was a guy behind the college the other day that had a fire go in
Yeah, absolutely refused to come to shelter
I mean, and it was one of the cold snacks like Sunday
Nothing just reviewed you would on the
I had a conversation with somebody who volunteered for that and some of the comments that were being shared with her
Where is too close to the police station?
What they're gonna bother you? I mean
I'm just saying what was said. I'm not saying it's right wrong or indifferent
I'm just saying that was the comments that the person who was volunteering working there said that they had very few people even
Stay there and
And the comments were coming across that because it was so close to the police station people were to about
cops coming in and checking to see who was there. I mean, I don't think they would have ever happened, but
But I mean
That's just the truth of what was being said
I'll pile on to what both of these guys said
You know watch our water crew yesterday
We're gonna water like those blown water everywhere
Unbelievable that they were out there for that many hours and stuck with it. I got that done
And the same thing with you know, we're other crews that helped set up for the shelter and stuff
What your people do is amazing really is and I gave Kudos to all the city employees because
Whether it be our water crew or electric crew or fire department or police department
They show up every day and get the job done and it makes our jobs easier. I know the community doesn't tell you thank you enough
And I wish they didn't tell you more because of that you guys nothing would run
So I appreciate each one of you guys. I appreciate your employees. Please pass that along for me
Thank you because
It's important what they do and I don't always recognize for the hard work and it is appreciate so I do want to throw one more shout out out there
So the Tyler and his group Derek. I had made a comment that was brought to my attention about the park in the area over there in Rockdale
It was a really dark
The week after I said it to things would have like a Christmas tree and I've got nothing but positive feedback from the neighborhood
That was awesome. I appreciate that and that's the I want to pop on that too
because when we do send stuff to you guys for a week here,
you guys are right on it, and it's much appreciated.
I know I had a lady that I did not send you guys a message,
but she guys were a place to lie in front of her house,
and she sent me a message with her post-treat lit up,
thanking me for the light, which I had nothing to do with.
But she said at the first time, she could walk her dog
and bite and feel safe and her own neighborhood.
So those little things matter, and I think people are trying
to pick up a little bit more that they just need to say,
thank you, and once we're on, I hope that's the case.
But you guys just keep up the good work.
So, and I'm telling you that water didn't yesterday.
I was blown away, and I stopped, because I was going
to get those got some coffee, and Molly was already on it,
and getting them coffee, so I didn't have to.
But that's another thing I want to say is,
that was the water crew there, fixing that.
That electric crew guys are helping.
Yeah, electric crew guys get wet in the water too.
So, that's teamwork.
I appreciate it for all of you.
And city manager communications.
Well, I would say thank you to you all as well.
All your support matters.
It helps bring in the community together, communicating, helping us
find groups to come together, and help the facility up,
because this was not necessarily a city deal.
Having that shelter, we had the facility.
Kevin and his team came in, made it available, got the tarps down.
They put the heat, you could only keep that old gymnasium, so warm.
And they do a great job, but having a rick at his folks, step up,
and I mean, there were so much food here, and people working,
and they did a great job coming in and training people,
we couldn't do this without that group.
So, it's really a blessing that in this community,
we have the team to come together and do that, because again,
they were a team without facility, and we were a facility without a team,
and it was a great opportunity to show what we can do.
We're going to be having a follow up meeting with them to kind of see what worked well,
and what we can do better, because we want to be able to repeat something like that.
If we've got a good opportunity to do a good thing, and it works well,
we'll figure out how to do it again when it's needed, but we need their help.
You know, when the show up today was telling me that one of the things we got to consider
is if the National Guard ever comes in,
they might be able to flood in O7, they took over the Civic Center.
That's where they housed, and so we might have to really kind of play ahead and think about,
in the event that we have a larger scope event, we'd have to rethink it,
but that being said, I think we've got a great interim opportunity here and what we can offer.
So, thanks to everybody that made that happen, and thanks to a great team,
everybody out there, Kevin, and your team.
They're all running around even today, as we were firing back up, the officer's opening up,
and we've got water coming in windows that are iced over,
and we should try to pop that stuff up and keep these...
building running and all my equipment running and it takes a village, but they all do it a great job.
Can't imagine doing this without everyone I'm 14 adjourned motion, 2, 2,